This is a story about you
这是关于你的故事
and me and your dog.
也关于我和你的狗
There was a time not long ago... before dogs.
不久之前  在狗出现之前
They didn't exist.
它们以前不存在
Now there are big ones, small ones, snugglers,
现在的狗有大有小 宠物狗
guardians, hunters.
守护犬  猎犬
Every kind of dog you could possibly want.
各式各样的狗
How did that happen?
怎么会这样
It's not just dogs.
不仅仅是狗
Where did all the different kinds
形形色色的各种生物
of living creatures come from?
都是从哪里来的呢
The answer is a transforming
power that sounds like something
答案是来自能量的转换  听上去可能
straight out of a fairy tale or myth,
像是童话或者神话
but it's no such thing.
但并非如此
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文字幕 @SaltyEggPain
宇    宙
时空探险之旅
第 2 集
分子做的一些事
Some of the Things That Molecules Do
Let's go back across 30,000
years to a time before dogs,
让我们回到3万年前 狗狗诞生前
when our ancestors lived in the endless winter
那时我们的祖先生活在最后一次冰河时代的
of the last ice age.
无尽冬夜
Our ancestors were wanderers
living in small bands.
我们的祖先小规模的群居 游荡着
They slept beneath the stars.
他们睡在星空下
The sky was their storybook, calendar,
星星就是他们的故事书  日历
an instruction manual for living.
生活指南
It told them when the bitter colds would come,
星星告诉他们严寒何时到来
when the wild grains would ripen,
谷物何时成熟
when the herds of caribou
and bison would be on the move.
鹿群和野牛群何时迁徙
Their idea of home was Earth itself.
他们对家的印象就是地球本身
But they lived in fear of other hungry creatures...
但是他们受到其他饥饿生物的威胁
the mountain lions and the bears
比如狮子和熊
that competed with them for the same prey
与他们抢夺同样地猎物
and the wolves that threatened to carry off and devour
还有狼群会掠食他们中
the most vulnerable among them.
最脆弱的同伴
All the wolves want to get at the bone,
所有的狼都想来分一杯羹
but most of them are too
frightened to come close enough.
但大部分都不敢靠的太近
Their fear is due to high levels
他们的恐惧来自血液中
of stress hormones in their blood.
高浓度的应激激素
It's a matter of survival.
这是生死攸关的问题
Because coming too close to humans can be fatal.
因为靠的太近可能很致命
But a few wolves-- due to natural variations--
但也有些狼  因为自然差异
have lower levels of those hormones.
这种激素浓度较低
This makes them less afraid of humans.
使得它们不是那么惧怕人类
This wolf has discovered
这头狼和他祖先
what a branch of his ancestors figured out
中的一个分支发现了同样的情况
some 15,000 years ago...
大约在1万5千年前
an excellent survival strategy;
一个完美的生存策略
the domestication of humans.
人类的驯化
Let the humans do the hunting,
don't threaten them,
在人类捕猎时别威胁到他们
and they'll let you scavenge their garbage.
他们会允许你以残渣为食
You'll eat more regularly,
you'll leave more offspring,
你吃的更规律 就可以繁衍更多的后代
and those offspring will inherit your disposition.
这些后代会继承你的性情
This selection for tameness
这种驯养的淘汰方式
would be reinforced with each generation
效果逐代加强
until that line of wild wolves evolves into...
直到这一系的野狼进化为
dogs.
狗
You might call this "survival of the friendliest."
你可以称它为最友善的生存
Then as now, this was a good
deal for the humans, too.
现在看来 这也是对人类非常有利的
The scavenging dogs weren't just a sanitation squad.
那些吃剩饭的狗并不只是收拾垃圾
They worked security.
他们也是保安力量
As this interspecies partnership
continued over time,
随着这种不同物种间的合作
the dogs' appearance changed also.
狗的外貌也发生了改变
Cuteness became a selective advantage.
可爱变成了优胜劣汰时的优势
The more adorable you were,
the better chance you had
你越可爱 就有更大的机会活下去
to live and pass on your genes
to another generation.
并把你的基因传递给下一代
What began as an alliance of convenience
起先是为了便利而结成的联盟
became a friendship that deepened over time.
变成了越来越深厚的友谊
To see what happens next,
接下来发生了什么
let's leave our distant ancestors
我们略过2万年前的先祖
of some 20,000 years ago to visit the more recent past
看看不是很久以前的古人
during an intermission in the Ice Age.
在冰河时代的间歇期
This break in the climate starts a revolution.
平和的气候带来了一场变革
Instead of wandering, people are settling down.
人类不再流浪  而是定居下来
There's something new in the world... villages.
新的事物出现了  村庄
People still hunt and gather,
人们依然在打猎和采集食物
but now they also produce food and clothing...
但也开始了制造食物和衣服
agriculture.
农业
The wolves have traded their freedom
狼用他们的自由
in exchange for a steady meal.
来交换稳定的食物供应
They've given up their right to choose a mate.
他们放弃了选择伙伴的权利
Now the humans choose for them.
人类替他们选择
They consistently kill off
the dogs that can't be trained;
他们消灭无法被驯服的狗
the ones that bite the feeding hand.
那些会咬人的狗
And they breed the dogs that please them.
他们繁育那些讨喜的狗
They nurture those dogs that do their bidding...
让这些狗服从命令
hunting, herding, guarding, hauling,
打猎  放牧  守卫  拖拽重物
and keeping them company.
陪伴人类
From every litter,
从每一窝小狗中
the humans select the puppies they like best.
选择那些他们最喜欢的
Over the generations, the dogs evolve.
一代接一代 狗进化了
This kind of evolution is called "artificial selection"
称之为 人工选择
or "breeding."
或者  饲养
Turning wolves into dogs was
the first time
把狼变成狗 是人类第一次
we humans took evolution into our own hands.
亲手干预进化过程
And we've been doing it ever since
从那以后我们改进了
to shape all the plants
and animals that we depend on.
对我们有用的植物和动物
In a blink of cosmic time,
just 15,000 or 20,000 years,
弹指一挥间 大约1万5千到2万年里
we turned gray wolves into all the kinds of dogs
我们把灰狼改变成为了各种各样的可爱的狗
we love today.
Think of it.
想想看
Every breed of dog you've ever seen
各个品种的狗
was sculpted by human hands.
都是人类塑造出来的
Many of our best friends--
the most popular breeds--
其中大部分 最受欢迎的品种
were created in only the last few centuries.
都是最近几百年培育出来的
The awesome power of evolution
进化的强大力量
transformed the ravenous wolf
将穷凶极恶的狼
into the faithful shepherd...
变成忠心耿耿的牧羊犬
...who protects the herd and drives the wolf away.
保护 看守羊群 并驱赶狼群
Artificial selection turned
the wolf into the shepherd
人工培育 把狼变成狗
and the wild grasses into wheat and corn.
把野草变成小麦和玉米
In fact, almost every plant
and animal that we eat today
事实上 大部分我们食用的植物和动物
was bred from a wild, less-edible ancestor.
都是来自野生的 不可食用的品种
If artificial selection can work such profound changes
如果强大的人工选择可以在1万到1万5千年间
in only 10,000 or 15,000 years,
带来如此巨大的变化
what can natural selection do
那么大自然的选择淘汰
operating over billions of years?
在上百万年间可以做到怎样的程度呢
The answer is all the beauty and diversity of life.
形形色色美好的生命就是答案
How does it work?
怎么做到得
Our Ship of the Imagination
can take us anywhere in space
我们的想象之舟可以带我们去任何地方
and time, even to the hidden microcosmos,
任何时间 甚至看不见的小宇宙
where one kind of life can be
transformed into another.
在那里 生命可以完成蜕变
Come with me.
跟我来
May not seem like it,
看上去可能不像
but we've been living in an ice age
我们曾经生活在冰河时期
for the last two million years.
长达2百万年之久
This just happens to be
one of the long intermissions.
现在只是其中一个间歇期
For most of those two million years,
2百万年间的大部分时期
the climate has been cold and dry.
气候又冷又干
The North Polar ice cap extended much farther south
北极冰盖比今天所看到的范围更大
than it does today.
In one of those long, cold glacial periods
在这漫长的冰川期
when the winter sea ice
stretched from the North Pole
从北极来的冬季海水冰
all the way down to what is now Los Angeles,
一直延伸至今日洛杉矶所在的位置
great bears roamed the frozen
wastes of Ireland.
大灰熊在冰冻荒芜的爱尔兰游荡
This might look like an ordinary bear,
这头熊看上去很普通
but something extraordinary
is happening inside her.
但是她的内在却有着不平凡的变化
Something that will give rise
to a new species.
一股催生新物种的力量
In order to see it,
要探究这股力量
we'll need to descend down
to a much smaller scale,
我们要把比例尺调整到
to the cellular level,
细胞级别
so that we can explore
the bear's reproductive system.
这样才能探究熊的生殖系统
We'll take the subclavian artery through the heart.
我们通过锁骨下的动脉穿过心脏
Almost there.
快到了
Those are some of her eggs.
那是一些她的卵子
To see what's going on in one of them,
要想了解这些卵子的详情
we'll have to get even smaller.
我们必须变得更小
We'll have to shrink down to the molecular level.
缩小到分子级别
Our Ship of the Imagination is now so small,
我们的想象之舟有多小呢
you could fit a million of them into a grain of sand.
只有一颗沙粒的百万分之一
See those guys over there
strutting along those girders?
看到那些阔步前进的小家伙吗
They are proteins
called kinesin.
他们是蛋白质 叫做驱动蛋白
These kinesin are part of the transport crew
这些驱动蛋白是搬运工
that's busy moving cargo around the cell.
忙碌地在细胞间传递货物
How alien they seem.
长得就像外星人
And yet these tiny creatures--
and beings like them--
它们和其他长相类似的小家伙
are a part of every living cell,
including the ones inside you.
存在于每个活细胞中 包括我们的细胞
If life has a sanctuary,
如果生命体也有圣殿
it's here in the nucleus
which contains our DNA...
那就是细胞核 包含了我们的DNA
the ancient scripture
of our genetic code.
我们遗传密码的远古圣经
And it's written in a language
that all life can read.
由所有生命体都能理解的语言写成
DNA is a molecule shaped
like a long twisted ladder
DNA是一种长螺旋阶梯状的分子
or double helix.
也叫双螺旋结构
The rungs of the ladder are made
阶梯的横档是由4种
of four different kinds of smaller molecules.
不同的小分子组成
These are the letters of the genetic alphabet.
这些就是基因字母表中的字母
Particular arrangements of those letters spell out
这些字母的特定排列组合
the instructions for all living things,
产生出针对所有生命体的指令
telling them how to grow, move, digest,
告诉它们如果生长 移动 消化
sense the environment, heal, reproduce.
感知环境 愈合 繁殖
The DNA double helix is a molecular machine
DNA双螺旋就是一台分子机器
with about 100 billion parts called "atoms."
由1千亿称之为原子的部件组成
There are as many atoms
in a single molecule of your DNA
单个DNA分子中的原子数量
as there are stars in a typical galaxy.
多的就像银河系中的繁星数量
The same is true for dogs
和狗一样
and bears
和熊一样
and every living thing.
和所有生物一样
We are, each of us, a little universe.
我们 每一个人 就是一个小宇宙
The DNA message handed down from cell to cell
DNA信息在细胞与细胞间
and from generation to generation is copied
也在一代接一代的繁衍中异常谨慎地复制着
with extreme care.
The birth of a new DNA molecule
begins when an unwinding protein
当一条松开的蛋白质分开双螺旋的两条边
separates the two strands of the double helix,
拆开中间的横档
breaking the rungs apart.
新的DNA分子就诞生了
Inside the liquid of the nucleus,
细胞核的液体中
the molecular letters of
the genetic code float freely.
遗传密码的分子字母自由的游动
Each strand of the helix copies its lost partner,
双螺旋的其中一边复制着失去的另外一边
resulting in two identical DNA molecules.
变成两个完全一样的DNA分子
That's how life reproduces genes and transmits them
这就是生命体繁衍和传递基因的方式
from one generation to the next.
代代相传
When a living cell divides in two,
当一个活细胞分裂成两个
each one takes away with it
a complete copy of the DNA.
每个细胞都带有一份完整的DNA
A specialized protein proofreads to make sure
一种特定的蛋白质负责校对
that only the right letters are accepted
确保只接受正确的字母
so that the DNA is accurately copied.
这保证了DNA的准确复制
But nobody's perfect.
但是没有什么是完美的
Occasionally, a proofreading error slips through,
偶尔 校对也会发生失误
making a small, random change in the genetic instructions.
在遗传指令中产生了细微的随机变化
A mutation has occurred in the bear's egg cell.
这头熊的卵子细胞中发生了突变
A random event as tiny as
this one can have consequences
如此细微的随机事件也会带来
on a far grander scale.
很大的影响
That mutation altered the gene
that controls fur color.
突变改变了控制毛皮颜色的基因
It will affect the production of dark pigment in the fur
它影响了这只熊的后代的深色毛皮的产生
of the bear's offspring.
Most mutations are harmless.
大多数突变是无害的
Some are deadly.
有些是致命的
But a few, purely by chance,
can give an organism
少数 纯属偶然 使得某个生物
a critical advantage over the competition.
在竞争中获得重大优势
A year has passed.
1年后
Our bear is now a mother.
这只熊做了母亲
And as a result of that mutation,
作为突变的结果
one of her two cubs was born with a white coat.
其中一只熊宝宝生来就是白色的皮毛
When the cubs get old enough
to venture out on their own,
当两只熊长大到可以自己猎食时
which bear is more likely
哪头熊更可能
to be able to sneak up on unsuspecting prey?
悄悄地接近它们的猎物
The brown bear can be seen against the snow a mile away.
棕熊和雪区别明显  很远就能被察觉
The white bear prospers and passes on
白熊子孙满堂 并把它独特的基因
its own particular set of genes.
传递下去
This happens repeatedly.
这样的情况不断发生
Over succeeding generations,
再接下去的几代里
the gene for white fur spreads through
白色皮毛的基因散播遍及整个北极的熊
the entire population of Arctic bears.
The gene for dark fur loses out
深色皮毛的基因消亡在
in the competition for survival.
生存的竞争中
Mutations are entirely random and happen all the time.
突变是完全随机并且时刻发生的
But the environment rewards those
但是环境会奖励那些
that increase the chance for survival.
对生存有利的突变
It naturally selects the living things
大自然选择那些可以更好适应环境的生物
that are better suited to survive.
And that selection is the opposite of random.
这种选择绝对不是随机的
The two populations of bears separated,
两个种群的熊各自分开
and over thousands of years,
经过了上千年
evolved other characteristics that set them apart.
进化出各自独有的特征
They became different species.
它们变成了不同的物种
That's what Charles Darwin meant
这就是查尔斯 达尔文
by "the origin of species."
在《物种起源》中发表的思想
An individual bear doesn't evolve;
单个的熊不会进化
the population of bears evolves over generations.
一群熊在几代繁衍中进化
If the Arctic ice continues to dwindle
如果北极的冰日益减少
due to global warming, the polar bears may go extinct.
全球变暖的缘故 北极熊可能灭绝
They'll be replaced by brown bears,
它们会被棕熊取代
better adapted to the now defrosted environment.
可以更好地适应冰融后的环境
This is a different story from the one about the dogs.
这个故事和狗的进化不一样
No breeder guided these changes.
没有人去指导这个变化
Instead, the environment itself selects them.
它们都是由自然环境选择的
This is evolution by natural selection,
这就是自然选择
the most revolutionary concept in the history of science.
科学历史上最颠覆性的理论
Darwin first presented the evidence for this idea in 1859.
1859年 达尔文首次提出了支持这个理论的证据
The uproar it caused has never subsided.
它带来的争议从未消退
Why?
为什么
We all understand the twinge of discomfort
我们都可以理解那种令人不适的刺痛
at the thought that we share a common ancestor with the apes.
我们竟然是猩猩变的
No one can embarrass you like a relative.
亲戚最能让我们感到丢脸
Our closest ones, the chimpanzees,
我们的近亲  黑猩猩
they frequently behave inappropriately in public.
它们频繁在公共场合做出不当的举止
There's an understandable human need
人类想和它们保持距离也是可以理解的
to distance ourselves from them.
A central premise of traditional belief
传统信仰的核心前提
is that we were created separately
我们是造物者特制的
from all the other animals.
和其他动物有区别的
It's easy to see why this idea has taken hold.
这种观点也很容易被理解
It makes us feel... special.
它让我们觉得 与众不同
But what about our kinship with the trees?
如果我们和这些树是亲戚呢
How does that make you feel?
你又作何感想
Okay, here's a segment of the oak tree's DNA.
这是橡树DNA的一部分
Think of it like a bar code.
把它看做条形码
The instructions written in the code of life
生命代码的指令
tell the tree how to metabolize sugar.
告诉这个树如何分解糖分
Now let's compare it with the same section of my own DNA.
拿它和我自己的DNA作比较
The DNA doesn't lie.
DNA不会撒谎
This tree and me-- we're long-lost cousins.
这棵树就是我失散已久的表亲
And it's not just the trees.
不单单是树
If you go back far enough, you'll find that we share
如果回到很久以前 我们可以发现
a common ancestor with...
我们有着共同的祖先
the butterfly...
蝴蝶
gray wolf...
灰狼
mushroom...
蘑菇
shark...
鲨鱼
bacterium...
细菌
sparrow.
麻雀
What a family!
幸福的一家人
Other parts of the bar code vary
from species to species.
条形码的其他部分因人而异
That's what makes the difference
between an owl and an octopus.
这也使得猫头鹰和章鱼有所区别
Unless you have an identical twin,
除非你有一个同卵双胞胎
there's no one else in the universe
这个世界上不会有人
with the exact same DNA as you.
和你有着相同的DNA
Within other species, the genetic differences
其他的物种中 遗传基因的不同
provide the raw material for natural selection.
为自然选择提供了原材料
The environment selects which genes survive and multiply.
环境决定了什么基因可以生存繁衍
When it comes to the genetic instructions for life's
说到生物遗传基因的指令中
most basic functions--
最基本的功能
say, digesting sugars-- we and other species
比方说分解糖分  我们和其他物种
are almost identical.
几乎一致
That's because those functions are so basic to life,
因为这些是生命最基本的功能
they evolved before the various life-forms
它们在各种不同生命形式诞生前
branched off from each other.
就已经进化完成
This is our Tree of Life.
这就是我们的生命之树
Science has made it possible
科学使我们可以
for us to construct this family tree
为地球上的所有生物
for all the species of life on Earth.
绘制这份家谱
Close genetic relatives occupy
the same branch of the tree,
相近基因的亲戚住在同一根的枝干上
while more distant cousins are farther away.
差异越大住的越远
Each twig is a living species.
每支细枝都是一个物种
And the trunk of the tree
represents the common ancestors
主杆代表着地球上所有生命的
of all life on Earth.
共同祖先
The stuff of life is so malleable
生命具有很高的可塑性
that once it got started,
the environment molded it
生命一旦出现  环境就开始
into a staggering variety of forms--
将它塑造出惊人数量的不同形态
10,000 times more than we can possibly show here.
比我们所能展示的还多1万倍
Biologists have catalogued
生物学家已经编录了
a half a million different kinds of beetles alone.
50万种不同的甲壳虫
Not to mention the numberless varieties
更别提那些数之不尽的细菌
of bacteria.
There are many millions of living species
有几百万种不同种类的
of animals and plants,  most of them
动物和植物  其中大部分
still unknown to science.
依然未知
Think of that--
we have yet to make contact
这么说吧  我们至今还没有见过
with most of the forms of terrestrial life.
大部分的陆栖生物
That's how many kinds of life there are
我们这个小小星球上就是有这么多种的生命
on this tiny planet alone.
The Tree of Life extends its feelers in all directions,
生命之树将触角伸向所有的方向
finding and exploiting what works,
探寻可行的办法
creating new environments
为新的生命形式
and opportunities for new forms.
创造新的环境和机会
The Tree of Life is three and a half billion years old.
生命之树已经35亿岁了
That's plenty of time to develop
时间已经长的可以发展出
an impressive repertoire of tricks.
所有令人惊奇的本领
Evolution can disguise an animal
进化可以使一种动物
as a plant...
伪装成植物
...taking thousands of generations
花费了数千代的努力
to contrive an elaborate costume
去设计一套精心制作的服饰
that fools predators into looking elsewhere
用来欺骗捕食者的眼睛
for someone to eat.
Or it can disguise a plant as an animal,
或者植物伪装成动物的模样
evolving blossoms that take on
the appearance of a wasp--
花朵进化出黄蜂般的外表
the orchid's way of fooling real wasps into pollinating it.
兰花就用这种方式诱使黄蜂为他授粉
This is the awesome
这就是强大的
shape-shifting power of natural selection.
自然选择下的变形本领
Among the dense, tangled limbs of the vast Tree of Life...
在密集杂乱的巨大生命之树上
you are here.
你在这里
One tiny branch among countless millions.
数不胜数的众多分支中的一小支
Science reveals that all life on Earth is one.
科学揭示了所有生命本是同源
Darwin discovered the actual mechanis of evolution.
达尔文发现了真正的进化机制
The prevailing belief was that the complexity
过去普遍的观点是
and variety of life must be the work
种类繁多的生命
of an intelligent designer, who created each
必然是有造物主创造的
of these millions of different species separately.
分别创造了几百万种不同的生物
Living things are just too intricate, it was said,
这种观点认为 生物实在是太复杂了
to be the result of unguided evolution.
不可能由未经引导的进化而来
Consider the human eye,
就像人的眼睛
a masterpiece of complexity.
一个极其复杂的杰作
It requires a cornea,
要有角膜
iris, lens, retina,
虹膜 晶状体 视网膜
optic nerves, muscles,
视神经 肌肉群
let alone the brain's elaborate neural network
再配合大脑复制的神经网络
to interpret images.
才能产生一幅图像
It's more complicated than any device
它远比其他任何一个人类制造的
ever crafted by human intelligence.
物体要来的复杂
Therefore, it was argued,
所以 结论是
the human eye can't be the result
人眼不可能是无意识的
of mindless evolution.
进化产物
To know if that's true,
we need to travel across time
要了解真相 我们需要回到
to a world before there were eyes to see.
我们有能力看之前
In the beginning,
最初
life was blind.
生命都是瞎子
This is what our world looked like
这是我们的世界 40亿年前的样子
four billion years ago,
before there were any eyes to see.
那时还没有眼睛可以视物
Until a few hundred million years passed,
直到几亿年过去
and then, one day,
突然有一天
there was a microscopic copying error
一个细菌的DNA产生了
in the DNA of a bacterium.
细微的复制错误
This random mutation gave that microbe
这个随机的突变给了这个微生物
a protein molecule that absorbed sunlight.
一个可以吸收阳光的蛋白质分子
Want to know what the world looked like
想知道感光细菌的世界是什么样子的吗
to a light-sensitive bacterium?
Take a look at the right side of the screen.
看看屏幕的右边
Mutations continued to occur at random,
突变继续随机的发生
as they always do in any
population of living things.
在其他所有的生物身上
Another mutation
另一个突变
caused a dark bacterium to flee intense light.
使得细菌可以逃离强烈的阳光
What is going on here?
发生了什么事
Night and day.
黑夜和白昼
Those bacteria that could tell light from dark
这些可以区分亮光的细菌
had a decisive advantage over the ones that couldn't.
相对其他细菌有了一个决定性的优势
Why?
为什么
Because the daytime brought harsh, ultraviolet light
因为日光带着强烈的紫外线
that damages DNA.
会损伤DNA
The sensitive bacteria fled the intense light
敏感的细菌避开强烈的光线
to safely exchange their DNA in the dark.
在暗处安全的交换DNA
They survived in greater numbers
它们比其他生活在表面的细菌
than the bacteria that stayed at the surface.
更多的存活下来
Over time, those light-sensitive proteins
日积月累 这些光敏蛋白质
became concentrated in a pigment spot
在更高级的单细胞生物身上
on the more advanced, one-celled organism.
浓缩成一个色素点
This made it possible to find the light,
这使寻找光亮成为可能
an overwhelming advantage
对于需要阳光合成食物的
for an organism that harvests sunlight to make food.
生命体来说 这是个压倒性的优势
Here's a flatworm's-eye view of the world.
这是扁平虫眼中的世界
This multi-celled organism
这个多细胞生物
evolved a dimple in the pigment spot.
在色素点中进化出一个小坑
The bowl-shaped depression
碗状的凹痕
allowed the animal to distinguish light from shadow
使动物可以区别明暗
to crudely make out objects in its vicinity,
大致看出周围的物体
including those to eat and those that might eat it...
包括食物和天敌
a tremendous advantage.
非常了不起的优势
Later, things became a little clearer.
随后 影像更清晰了
The dimple deepened
小坑变深了
and evolved into a socket with a small opening.
进化成一个有开口的凹槽
Over thousands of generations,
经过几千代
natural selection was slowly sculpting the eye.
自然选择逐渐塑造出眼睛
The opening contracted to a pinhole covered
开放的地方凝聚成一个小孔
by a protective transparent membrane.
由一层保护性的透明薄膜覆盖
Only a little light could enter the tiny hole,
只允许一点点的光线透过小孔
but it was enough to paint a dim image
但也足够在敏感的眼睛内部表面
on the sensitive inner surface of the eye.
描绘出一幅模糊的图像
This sharpened the focus.
这演变出了聚焦
A larger opening would have let in more light
更大的孔可以让更多的光线通过
to make a brighter image but one that was out of focus.
产生更亮的图像  但却失去了焦点
This development launched the visual equivalent
这个新形态引发了视觉的军备竞赛
of an arms race.
The competition needed to keep up to survive.
竞争者们需要跟上才能生存
But then a splendid new feature of the eye evolved,
一个新的绝妙特征出现了
a lens that provided both
brightness and sharp focus.
可以同时保证亮度和清晰焦点的晶状体
In the eyes of primitive fish,
在远古的鱼类眼中
the transparent gel near
the pinhole formed into a lens.
小孔附近的透明胶体形成了晶状体
At the same time, the pinhole enlarged
同时 小孔扩大了
to let in more and more light.
允许更多的光线通过
Fish could now see in high-def,
鱼的视界高清了
both close up and far away.
不论远近
And then something terrible happened.
然而 可怕的事情发生了
Have you ever noticed that a straw in a glass of water
你注意到一杯水中的吸管
looks bent at the surface of the water?
看上去在水面处是弯的吗
That's because light bends when it goes from one medium
那是因为光线从一个介质进入另一个介质时发生了折射
to another, say from water to air.
就像从水到空气
Our eyes originally evolved to see in water.
我们的眼睛最初是为了在水中视物
The watery fluid in those eyes neatly
眼中的水状液体巧妙地
eliminated the distortion of that bending effect.
消除了折射的影响
But for land animals,
但是对于陆地动物
the light carries images from dry air
在空气中成像的光线
into their still-watery eyes.
进入它们湿润的眼睛
That bends the light rays,
光线发生折射
causing all kinds of distortions.
造成全面的失真
When our amphibious ancestors left the water for the land,
当我们的两栖祖先从水中登陆时
their eyes, exquisitely evolved to see in water,
原本在水中精确视物的眼睛
were lousy for seeing in the air.
却在空气中一塌糊涂
Our vision has never been as good since.
从那时起我们的视力一直不好
We like to think of our eyes as state-of-the-art,
我们一直认为我们的眼睛是最高级的
but 375 million years later,
但直到3.75亿年后
we still can't see things right in front of our noses
我们依然无法看清近在眼前的东西
or discern fine details in near darkness
或者像鱼那样在昏暗环境中辨别细节
the way fish can.
When we left the water,
当我们离开水里时
why didn't nature just start over again
为什么大自然不能从新来过
and evolve us a new set of eyes
进化出一对新的眼睛
that were optimal for seeing in the air?
可以在空气中清晰视物
Nature doesn't work that way.
大自然并不是这样的
Evolution reshapes existing structures over generations,
进化过程对于已有的结构的改变
adapting them with small changes.
是世世代代的慢慢适应
It can't just go back to the drawing board
而不可能一切推倒重来
and start from scratch.
At every stage of its development, the evolving eye
进化中眼睛 在每一步的发展中
functioned well enough
都为我们的生存提供了极大的优势
to provide a selective advantage for survival.
And among animals alive today,
we find eyes
在现在存活的动物身上 我们发现了
at all these stages of development.
各个发展阶段的眼睛
And all of them function.
它们都很实用
The complexity of the human eye poses
人类眼睛的复杂程度对进化过程来说
no challenge to evolution by natural selection.
没有丝毫难度
In fact, the eye and all of biology makes no sense
without evolution.
事实上 没有进化就根本无法解释眼睛和其他生物学
In fact, the eye and all of biology makes no sense
without evolution.
事实上 没有进化就根本无法解释眼睛和其他生物学
Some claim that evolution is just a theory,
有人说进化论只是一种理论
as if it were merely an opinion.
只不过是一种观点
The theory of evolution, like the theory of gravity,
进化论就和万有引力定律一样
is a scientific fact.
是科学的事实
Evolution really happened.
进化确有其事
Accepting our kinship with all life on Earth
承认我们和其他生物出自同源
is not only solid science.
并不只是严谨的科学
In my view, it's also a soaring spiritual experience.
在我看来 这也是一种崇高的心灵体验
Because evolution is blind,
因为进化是盲目地
it cannot anticipate or adapt
to catastrophic events.
它无法预测或改变悲剧的发生
The Tree of Life has some broken branches.
生命之树有一些断裂的分支
Many of them were severed in the five greatest catastrophes
其中大部分发生在5次最大的灾难中
that life has ever known.
Somewhere, there's a memorial
某个地方 有着一座纪念堂
to the multitude of lost species,
纪念着消失的物种
the Halls of Extinction.
灭绝物种的纪念堂
Come with me.
随我来
_
Welcome to the Halls of Extinction.
欢迎来到灭绝物种的纪念堂
A monument to the broken branches of the Tree of Life.
纪念着生命之树上的断枝
For every single one of the millions of species
对于依然存在的上百万种生物来说
alive today, perhaps a thousand others have perished.
可能上千种正在垂死挣扎
Most of them died out in the everyday competition
它们中大部分在与其他生命形式的日常竞争中绝种
with other life-forms.
But many of them were swept away
in vast cataclysms
但也有很多是被地球上无法抗拒的大灾难灭绝
that overwhelmed the planet.
In the last 500 million years,
在过去的5亿年里
this has happened five times.
发生过5次
Five mass extinctions that devastated life on Earth.
5次灭绝地球生命的大灾难
The worst one of all happened some 250 million years ago,
最惨的一次发生在2.5亿年前
at the end of an era
一个纪元的终结
known as the Permian.
称之 二叠纪
Trilobites were armored animals that hunted
三叶虫像装甲部队一样
in great herds across the seafloor.
成群结队的在海床上肆虐
They were among the first animals to evolve
它们是第一批进化出可以成像的眼睛的动物
image-forming eyes.
Trilobites had a good long run, some 270 million years.
三叶虫繁荣了大约2.7亿年
Earth was once the planet of the trilobites.
地球曾是三叶虫的天下
But now they're all gone, extinct.
但它们现在都没了 绝种了
The last of them were swept from life's stage
它们中最后的一部分
along with countless other species
也随着其他物种一起
in an unparalleled environmental disaster.
在空前的环境灾难中绝种了
The apocalypse began in what is now Siberia,
大灾难发生在今日西伯利亚的位置
with volcanic eruptions on a scale unlike anything
一场规模无比巨大的火山喷发
in human experience.
Earth was very different then,
那时地球很不一样
with one single supercontinent and one great ocean.
只有一个超质大陆板块和一片大洋
Relentless floods of fiery lava
无情的滚烫的熔浆
engulfed an area larger than Western Europe.
洪水般吞没了比西欧还大的区域
The pulsing eruptions went on for
hundreds of thousands of years.
断断续续的喷发持续了几十万年
The pulsing eruptions went on for
hundreds of thousands of years.
断断续续的喷发持续了几十万年
The molten rock
融化的岩石
ignited coal deposits and polluted the air
点燃了煤层 并且 污染了大气
with carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases.
充斥着二氧化碳和其他温室气体
This heated the Earth
地球温度升高
and stopped the ocean currents from circulating.
洋流停止了流动
Noxious bacteria bloomed,
有害的细菌迅速繁殖
but nearly everything else in the seas died.
海中其他生物几乎全部灭绝
The stagnant waters belched
deadly hydrogen sulfide gas into the air,
腐臭的水散发出致命的硫化氢气体
The stagnant waters belched
deadly hydrogen sulfide gas into the air,
腐臭的水散发出致命的硫化氢气体
which suffocated most of the land animals.
导致大多数陆地生物窒息
Nine in ten of all species on the planet went extinct.
百分之九十的物种灭绝
We call it...
我们称之为
The Great Dying.
大灭绝
Life on Earth came so near to being wiped out
地球上的生命差一点全部绝种
that it took more than ten million years to recover.
需要花费上千万年才能恢复
But new life-forms slowly evolved
但是新的生命形式在慢慢进化
to fill the openings left by the Permian holocaust.
开始填补由二叠纪大屠杀遗留的空缺
Among the biggest winners were the dinosaurs.
恐龙就是其中的大赢家
Now the Earth was their planet.
现在地球是它们的天下
Their reign continued for over 150 million years.
它们的统治持续了1.5亿年
Until it, too, came crashing down
也是在一次大灾难中
in another mass extinction.
不可避免的土崩瓦解
Life on Earth has taken quite a beating over the eons.
地球上的生命从太古时期就饱受摧残
And yet it's still there.
却依然存在
The tenacity of life is mind-boggling.
生命顽强得令人惊讶
We keep finding it where no one thought it could be.
我们总是能找到一条意想不到的生存之路
That nameless corridor?
看到那条无名走廊吗
That's for another day.
以后再说
I know an animal that can live in boiling water
有种动物可以活在沸腾的水中
or in solid ice.
或者坚固的冰层中
It can go ten years without a drop of water.
可以10年不喝一滴水
It can travel naked in the cold vacuum
可以不加防护的穿过寒冷真空
and intense radiation of space and will return unscathed.
并且充满强烈辐射的太空 而毫发无损
The tardigrade, or water bear.
节肢动物 又叫  缓步类动物
It's equally at home atop the tallest mountains
生活在最高的高山还是最深的海沟
and in the deepest trenches of the sea.
对它们来说没有区别
And in our own backyards, where they live among the moss
它们生活在苔藓中  就在我们周围
in countless numbers.
数也数不清
You've probably never noticed them
你可能从没注意到它们
because they're so small.
因为它们太小了
About the size of a pinpoint.
差不多针尖大小
But they're tough.
但它们很坚韧
The tardigrades have survived all five mass extinctions.
节肢动物从所有的5次大灾难中幸存下来
They've been in business for a half a billion years.
它们存在了5亿年之久
We used to think that life was finicky,
我们一直认为生命很挑剔
that it would only take hold where it was
他只能接受
not too hot, not too cold,
不太冷 不太热
not too dark or salty or acidic or radioactive.
不太暗 不咸 不酸 没辐射 的地方
And whatever you do, don't forget to add water.
还有 不管怎么样 别忘了喝水
We were wrong.
我们错了
As the hardy tardigrade demonstrates,
节肢动物证明我们错了
life can endure conditions
生命可以承受人类绝对无法生存的环境
that would mean certain death for us humans.
But differences between us and life found
但是我们和那些生活在最极端环境下的生物
in even the most extreme environments on our planet
are only variations on a single theme,
只有少许的区别
dialects of a single language.
就像一种语言中的不同方言
The genetic code of Earth life.
地球生命的遗传密码
But what would life be like on other worlds?
其他世界的生命又是什么样的呢
Worlds with a completely different history,
有着完全不同历史的世界
chemistry and evolution from our planet?
和我们完全不同的化学反应和进化过程
There's a distant world I want to take you to--
我想带你去一个遥远的世界
a world far different from our own,
一个和我们这个截然不同的世界
but one that may harbor life.
可能藏有生命
If it does, it promises to be unlike anything
如果有 那绝对我们以前见过的都不同
we've ever seen before.
Clouds and haze completely hide the surface of Titan,
云雾完全包裹了泰坦（土卫六）的表面
Saturn's giant moon.
土星的大月亮
Titan reminds me a little bit of home.
泰坦和地球有点像
Like Earth, it has an atmosphere that's mostly nitrogen.
它也有主要以氮气组成的大气层
But it's four times denser.
但是比我们的稠密4倍
Titan's air has no oxygen at all.
空气中没有丝毫氧气
And it's far colder than anywhere on Earth.
比地球上任何地方都冷
But still... I want to go there.
我依然想去那里
We have to descend
我们必须下降
through a couple hundred kilometers of smog
几百公里的烟雾
before we can even see the surface.
才能看到它的表面
But hidden beneath lies a weirdly familiar landscape.
但是下面藏着我们熟悉的风景
Titan is the only other world in the solar system
泰坦是太阳系中除地球外唯一一个
where it ever rains.
下雨的地方
It has rivers and coastlines.
它有河流和海岸线
Titan has hundreds of lakes.
有几百个湖泊
One of them larger than Lake Superior in North America.
有一个比北美的苏必利尔湖还大
Vapor rising from the lakes
蒸汽从湖面升起
condenses and falls again as rain.
凝结落下变成雨
The rain feeds rivers,
雨落进河流
which carve valleys into the landscape,
河流将山谷雕刻出风景
just like on Earth.
就像地球
But with one big difference.
但有一个很大不同
On Titan, the seas and the rain
泰坦上 海和雨不是由水组成
are made not of water but of methane and ethane.
而是甲烷和乙烷
On Earth, those molecules form natural gas.
在地球上 这些分子组成天然气
On frigid Titan,
在寒冷的泰坦上
they're liquid.
它们是液态的
Titan has lots of water,
泰坦上有很多水
but all of it is frozen hard as rock.
但它们都冻的像石头一样硬
In fact, the landscape and mountains
事实上 这些风景和山脉
are made mainly of water ice.
都是水做的
At hundreds of degrees below zero,
零下几百度
Titan is far too cold for water to ever be liquid.
泰坦冷的永远不会有液态的水
Astrobiologists since Carl Sagan have wondered
天体生物学家一直在猜想
if life might swim in Titan's hydrocarbon lakes.
泰坦上的碳氢化合物湖水中是否有生命
The chemical basis for such life
这种生命的化学成分
would have to be entirely
different from anything we know.
一定和我们所知的都不一样
All life on Earth depends on liquid water.
所有的地球生命都需要水
And Titan's surface has none of that.
泰坦的表面没有水
But we can imagine other kinds of life.
但我们可以想象另一种生命
There might be creatures that inhale hydrogen
这种生物可能呼吸氢气
instead of oxygen.
而不是氧气
And exhale methane instead of carbon dioxide.
呼出甲烷 而不是二氧化碳
They might use acetylene instead
of sugar as an energy source.
乙炔可能是它们的能量来源 而不是糖
How could we find out if such creatures
我们怎样才能找到它们
rule a hidden empire beneath the oil-dark waves?
如果它们的帝国躲藏在这石油般的海水下
We're diving down deep into the Kraken Sea,
我们潜下克拉肯海
named for the mythic Norse sea monster.
这是以北欧神话中的挪威海怪命名
Even if there is one of those down there,
就算真有海怪在这里
we probably couldn't see it.
我们也看不到
It's so dark.
太黑了
If you took all the oil and natural gas on Earth,
把地球上所有的石油和天然气加起来
it would amount to but a tiny fraction of Titan's reserves.
也只是泰坦储量的极小一部分
Let's turn on some lights.
让我们开点灯
We're now 200 meters beneath the surface.
现在是表面下200米
Did you see something?
看到什么了吗
Over there, by that vent.
那边 通道旁边
Maybe it was just my imagination.
也许我眼花了
I guess we'll have to come back
我们必须再来一次
if we want to find out for sure.
如果我们想要确切知道
There's one last story I want to tell you.
我想和你再说最后一个故事
And it's the greatest story science has ever told.
这是最伟大的科学故事
It's the story of life on our world.
关于我们世界上的生命
Welcome to the Earth of four billion years ago.
欢迎来到40亿年前的地球
This was our planet before life.
没有生命的星球
Nobody knows how life got started.
没人知道生命如何诞生
Most of the evidence
from that time was destroyed
撞击和侵蚀摧毁了大部分的证据
by impact and erosion.
Science works on the frontier
between knowledge and ignorance.
科学处在无知和已知之间
We're not afraid to admit what we don't know.
我们不怕承认我们不知道
There's no shame in that.
一点也不丢人
The only shame is to pretend
that we have all the answers.
丢人的是我们假装已经有了答案
Maybe someone watching this
也许观众中有人
will be the first to solve the mystery
会成为首个解开这个谜题的人
of how life on Earth began.
关于地球生命的起源
The evidence from living microbes
从现存的微生物得来的证据显示
suggest that their earliest ancestors
它们最古老的祖先
preferred high temperatures.
喜欢高温
Life on Earth may have arisen in hot water
地球生命也许出现在热水中
around submerged volcanic vents.
被水下的火山口环绕着
In Carl Sagan's original Cosmos series,
在卡尔·萨根的宇宙节目中
he traced the unbroken thread that stretches
他找到了
directly from the one-celled organisms
从将近40亿年前的单细胞生物到你之间的
of nearly four billion years ago...
不间断的
to you.
线索
Four billion years in 40 seconds.
相当于40秒的40亿年
From creatures who had yet to discern day from night
从不能分辨昼夜的生物
to beings who are exploring the cosmos.
到可以探索宇宙的生物
Those are some of the things that molecules do
这就是分子用40亿年时间进化的结果
given four billion years of evolution.
Sync and corrections by n17t01
www.addic7ed.com
中文字幕 @SaltyEggPain